<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ansvver to a declaration of the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly, to the whole Kirk and Kingdome of Scotland. Concerning present dangers, and duties relating to the covenant and religion. / By Borialis Guard.</title>
            <author>Ward, Nathaniel, 1578-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 25 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W778</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E433_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206198</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865372</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865372</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117612</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97130)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117612)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 68:E433[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ansvver to a declaration of the Commissioners of the Generall Assembly, to the whole Kirk and Kingdome of Scotland. Concerning present dangers, and duties relating to the covenant and religion. / By Borialis Guard.</title>
                  <author>Ward, Nathaniel, 1578-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Borialis = Nathaniel Ward.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 27 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland. --  General Assembly --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643) Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:117612:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>AN</hi> ANSVVER to a <hi>Declaration of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners of the Generall Aſſembly,</hi> To the whole Kirk and Kingdome of <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi> Concerning preſent dangers, and duties <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the Covenant and Religion.</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>By BORIALIS Guard.</byline>
            <p>THE Commiſſioners of the generall Aſſembly of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> are better read in bookes then men, and in this age of different opinions, they doe like thoſe at the confuſion of langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſort themſelves with whoſoever they be that jumpe with them in judgement, and thinke them honeſt and infallible in all things elſe, that hit right in <hi>Presbytery,</hi> though they but pretend to it, for ſuch there are that are neither <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> nor <hi>Independents,</hi> but cry up the one, becauſe it cries downe the other, and conſequently the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army that new model, which they hate for their vertues, not for their vices, their victories, not their tenets. But the greateſt Clerks are not always the wiſeſt men, nor ſee not the furtheſt into a milſtone. Some read Machiavell to do him, but they to undo him. There are Proteſtant Jeſuites of the ſhort robe, that can ſo diſguiſe themſelves as to cozen them of the long, and draw them (by an erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous credulity) to be really theirs, but by ſeeming that they are not.</p>
            <p>Al's not gold that gliſters, nor all true <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> or <hi>Patriots</hi> that are friends to <hi>Presbytery,</hi> or foes to the <hi>Army.</hi> Believe it, there are many Lay Lord-biſhops ſtil alive, that go diſguiſed in <hi>Presbyterian viſors,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know it is in vain to ſtrive againſt the ſtream, untill the wind blow right for them. Whoever he is that is an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> and intruſted for the Common-wealth, if he be factor for the King, he holds his principles as well Eccleſiaſticall as civill, and intends the Prerogative of both, time wil tel you ſo, though they do not; if God deceive them not, they wil deceive you; but hitherto they have miſſed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117612:2"/>their mark, travelled with iniquity, conceived miſcheif, and brought forth a lye, and ſo I am confident wil ever do. Only take heed you of partaking in other mens ſins, cal not evil good, nor good evil, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh; cry down error, but not the Army, leſt you change the act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, but not the tragedy, and cry up <hi>Presbytery,</hi> but not al <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> leſt as wiſe as you are, at laſt you conclude with a <hi>non putarem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King long ſince pawned both the word of a King and a Gentleman, and never yet redeemed them (for <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> obſerves, That at <hi>Rome</hi> its a maxime that Merchants, not Kings are to keepe their words, and <hi>Popery</hi> and he have been long bed-fellows) how to charm our <hi>Engliſh</hi> credulities, in his papers he calls God to witneſſe, another ſtate ſtratagem (it ſeems he is not witneſſe to oaths and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes) for nothing muſt be left unſaid or unaſſaid, and vouches con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for the continuing of Arch-biſhops, Biſhops and their lands, becauſe of the great Charter, and the curſe of the ſuperſtitious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors. So that the Eccleſiaſticall part of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> may not be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olated, nor <hi>Popiſh Epiſcopall</hi> lands alienated, but the civill or ſecular part of it may without offence, his peoples liberty, property, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates too fans ſcruple. Rare Chimiſtry, in conſcience, that can di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh without a difference, whereas indeed the root of the matter grows out of that old rotten maxime, <hi>No Biſhop, no King.</hi> He that can breake his word when he will, and make conſcience of what he wil, well he may ruine me, but he ſhall never deceive me, whoſe nature is ſo apparently diſagreeing to his office, and the duties belonging thereunto.</p>
            <p>From the Biſhops, whoſe abolition he tells you in his meſſage from the life of <hi>Wight,</hi> he cannot conſent to, he falls downe to the <hi>Militia,</hi> and does as unclearly conſent to that, as he clearly diſſented from the other; for firſt having laid a firme foundation of it to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in the Crown (as if the intereſt of the King were divers from that of the Kingdome, and the Crowne or Court to be preferred to the Common-wealth and its ſafety) by a ſtrong aſſertion, though he can neither preſſe men nor raiſe monies, and therefore cannot give his conſent to alienate it from the Crowne, and that becauſe of his truſt, which he is carefull to keep, but not to performe. Yea, ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is he of the Common-wealth, that he will not part with the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> no not to it ſelfe; but to give an infallible evidence of his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he will and he will not as to himſelfe depart with it during his reign, for firſt he ſayes he will conſent to an act that the whole power of the <hi>Militia</hi> ſhall during that time be ordered and diſpoſed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117612:2"/>by the two houſes, and after he comes with a mental reſervation, and ſaith, that neither his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> nor any other (by any authority deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved only from him (ſhall execute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> alſo that patents and commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions muſt go as formerly, <hi>viz.</hi> In his owne name, which to grant, it ſeems in court conſtruction, is to yeeld the right of the <hi>Militia</hi> to be in the Crown, the thing he drives at, for therby he gains more <hi>de jure</hi> then he loſes <hi>defacto,</hi> and is the more to be avoyded, and the legal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions of ſuch laws, and their tearms (bordering upon the Crown) both in this and other things of like nature ought to be made more explicate both to the vulgar peoples better underſtanding and Kings alſo, who only talke of a truſt to delude the people, and make it a ſtalking horſe to compaſſe their wills, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves abſolute, for what bears their image or ſuperſcription, it ſeems acording to the Court-credit is believed to be abſolutely and inſeparably theirs, as if the Crown were neither from, nor for the people; upon theſe tearms, in time, our monies will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to as well as our Laws, if care be not taken to prevent it. All monopolies have legall pretences, ſpecially Prerogative the worſt of all, wherewith his Majeſty is ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuouſly principled, that he is not counſellable in things touching common and publick good in a regular underſtanding of them according to the end and ordination of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. If the <hi>Militia</hi> be a flower of the Crown, pray, take it out, and ſtick a jewell i'th room on't which is both of more Majeſty and leſſe danger. From the <hi>Militia</hi> hee paſſes to the Armies arrears, and in time proffers to pay them 400000.{abl.} a great ſumme (it ſeems he hath been luſtily promiſed, and well adviſed, during his abode at <hi>Hampton-Court</hi>) but nothing to a willing minde, for ſo he hopes either to disband them (and then he knows how to re-inburſe that money, and as much more as will pay his arrears alſo) or to win them to himſelfe when he himſelfe becomes their pay maſter. And though he cannot depart with the <hi>Militia</hi> from the Crown, yet with the Court of Wards he can, though that alſo is inveſted in the Crown for protection and that of Infants, but this he is content to have taken away if it <hi>ſeem grievous,</hi> not the other though it <hi>bee</hi> ſo, to all. In the cloſe he mindes them of that which of all other muſt not be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, The diſſolving this Parliament to make way for another by due elections, that is wherein his partizent, Cavalliers and malignanrs may be both elected and electors, and ſo undoe all that either is already or ſhall hereafter be done by this, and then we have ſpun a long thread to little purpoſe, rare ſophiſtry and King craft. But I hope the people of <hi>England</hi> underſtand their intereſt better then thus to pull downe their props, and bring the houſe upon their heads, and that they will not take ſeemings for Beings, nor ſhadows for reallities. Take heed of diſguiſes and Court-masks, after ſo many blows and bullets, be not fool'd with faire words, and falſe fires. I pray your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty <hi>Beleeve your ſelfe a Subject, as well as a Sovereigne, and know that honeſty is the beſt policy. ſtand not on your head and ſhake your heels againſt heaven. Take God more into your counſells and your people into your care: It hath ever been the fault of Kings to ſtudy and practice policy more then piety, which hath brought ſo great miſeries upon many of them, and ſome to untimely ends, and what came of them after, God knows: what will it advantage you to gain the whole world (of power, and that power never ſo abſolute) and loſe your precious ſoule, you muſt dye as well as other men and leave your Crowne behinde you when you goe to the grave. Sure Kings either thinke they may ſin cum privilegio, or that thoſe things which are ſins in other men, as bing, diſſembling, oppreſſion, murder, rapine, ſwearing, forſwearing, are not ſo in them. Play
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117612:3"/>with your conſcience which one day will be ſerious with you, pretend, not protection when you intend deſtruction, be not deceived, Got wil not be mocked. How can you expect to be believed that never kept your word till this parliament, nor now if you could have broken it, the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours whereof hath been the cauſe of all this Civill war and blood-ſhed, beſides, you ſtill retain the ſame principles, entertain the ſame counſellours, and adhere to the ſame friends. It's true that Kings are called Gods, ſo are Devills to, therefore beare not your ſelfe upon that, as if there were no excellence in God but Power and Sovereignty, whereas he hath other Attributes and Properties beſides that are honourable, and that he is to be honoured for, as goodneſſe, mercy, juſtice protection, faithfulneſſe, initate him in theſe, ſo ſhalt you be Gods indeed, and though you muſt dye like men, yet ſhall you be as the Angels, for as ill Kings their condemnation is greater, ſo are good Kings their glorification higher, by how much their talent and ſtewardſhip on earth is above others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> are ſingular School-men in State-matters, and can diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh to a mote in the ſun. If the Parliament wiſh'd them to advance Southward, they retreated Northward by a Scotch figure, becauſe the North of <hi>England,</hi> is the South of <hi>Scotland.</hi> And lay juſt ſo long before <hi>Newarke,</hi> till by private confabulation, the King came to their Leaguer, and then, and there broke their word (but kept Covenant with the Parliaments <hi>Commiſſioners,</hi>) againſt their promiſe carrying away the King to <hi>Newcastle,</hi> in all poſt haſte, as if they had meant to have invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> in freedom, honour and ſafety, but no ſuch mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my Lord; touching the Kings dignity and greatneſſe; the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant only binds on this ſide <hi>Tweed,</hi> for beyond it He's little enough, but it ſeems they have bargained with him like the two Tribes and halfe, ſo they may have all beyond <hi>Jordan,</hi> theyle ſee him in ſafe poſſeſſion of <hi>Canaan,</hi> therefore, for that end, muſt there needs be a perſonall Treaty, and an invitation of him (whom they'le neer invite into <hi>Scotland</hi>) to <hi>London,</hi> in honour, ſafety, and freedome, the Kings own words, fiddle and ſtick, which makes <hi>Pregmaticus</hi> (the Court-jeſter) ready to leape out of his skin, for joy, to heare this tune played upon the <hi>Scotch</hi> Bag-pipes, ſo that hee'l goe neer to want a Theame, to time upon next week, being reconciled to this loyall fraternity. But they tell you the reaſon (and for my part I beleeve them) why they would have the King entertained at our coſt, becauſe they ſay their happineſſe is in him, for you muſt conſider the two great wheels of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Engine is now in perpetuall motion, the one to make <hi>England Scotland</hi> in matters Eccleſiaſticall, ſo that <hi>It is,</hi> and <hi>It is not ſo,</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> were urged in the Aſſembly like <hi>ipſe dixit</hi> in the Schools: the other is to make <hi>Scotland England</hi> in things ervill, and though an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man in <hi>Scotland</hi> muſt not untie the Kings ſhoe latchet, yet they ſtick not to propoſe to have the third part of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices about him here. They cry out of the abuſe offered a ſingle Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> and that no repaire is made, the whilſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117612:3"/>they ſanctuary <hi>Knox,</hi> and noſe us with <hi>Cheeſley</hi> thoſe arch incendiaries, that in whole volumes abuſed the whole ſtate of <hi>England,</hi> with breach of priviledge of Parliament to boot, which by Covenant is to be maintained, and they puniſhed, but a trick at maw will helpe that, for they can in their printed Papers (thoſe <hi>Scotch</hi> ſpectacles to blind <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen</hi>) take the Covenant in pieces, and quote it in abſtract Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions leaving out the principall verbe ſtill, the conditionate coherence of one thing with another, ſo that the reaſon why they ſo cry up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (wherein they have an excellent faculty) for tranſeendent Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters, is, becauſe they doe by the Covenant, as ſome Sectaries of theſe times doe by the Scriptures, bring their ſenſe to it, and not take ſenſe from it. And for moſt part what is their Religion? <hi>Presbyterie,</hi> they doe by it as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did by the Temple, worſhip it inſtead of God, and though ſwearing lying, and diſſembling, be even nationall vices amongſt them, yet by vertue of this bare badge they cry up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for <hi>the people of the Lord,</hi> as if heaven alſo could be caught by craft, but <hi>forma dat eſſe</hi> is a maxime undeniable with them, they are the beſt Chriſtians and Covenanters, becauſe the beſt <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> which they make their ſtaulking-horſe to catch citie and countrey, and the Aſſembly alſo, and their skreen to be-ſpatter the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Parliament, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the eleven Members, whoſe devotion to <hi>Presbyterie</hi> and the old Model, prefers them in favour above the reſt. From State Presbyters, <hi>Libera nos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But however let us doe them all good Offices, and keeps them at all due di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances mix not interests, keep Covenant in the intive plaine</hi> Engliſh <hi>ſenſe of it, avoid their tedious Haranys, pend ſpeeches, and voluminous Papers, which they only ſpeake to the Parliament first, to the end that after they may ſpeaks them in print to the people, which they know ſo great a body as the Parliament, preſſed with infinit and weighty buſineſſes cannot ſuddenly anſwer, and ſo think to cary the cauſe by cajoling the vulgar, and to divide betwixt the body reall and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative, and then the towas's their owns; too much Serpentins wiſdome to ſtand with the innocency of Doves. Thinke not the worſe of Presbytery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they Idolize it, but let power of godlineſſe and purity of worſhip get hand in hand. Let (in a word) the Parliament be true to their truſt, and</hi> England <hi>to it ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Army are men both in their effects and defects, and Engliſhmen alſo, the Kingdome have cauſe to ſay ſo, though too many are loath to ſpeake out their commendations for feare of diſcommindng them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Emulation as it tends towards imitation is a vertue, but as to envie a vice. In the way of their poſſeſſion they have done rare things,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117612:4"/>both as good Souldiers and true Patriots, in over-comming open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and diſappointing ſecret ones; but they are nothing ſo good at book-work, as at ſword-play; it cannot be denied but they make foul worke with Scripture and Pulpits, we never reade of Centurion Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and yet one built a Synagogue, and had ſo great a faith that Chriſt himſelfe marvelled at it, but he had deep humility withall, and yet a great Commander, moving in his ſphere as a Souldier, and not out of it. The other is renowed for a devout man, fearing God with all his houſe (there indeed it ſeems he taught as a <hi>pater familias</hi>) a Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Almes, and frequent in prayer, but neither before nor after <hi>Peter</hi> came to him, doe we read that he took upon him to preach: It ſeems though they were both gracious men, yet neither of them was a Gifted Borther. They abound in Victories, and ſo they doe in Errours, it is pity they ſhould doe ſo, that they who have beene the Lords Hoſte, and fought his Battails, ſhould now be the Devils ſeeds-men and ſow his Tares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet I would have them to bee not ſo bitter against the Reverend and godly Ministers in the Land, becauſe of Ordination, you know not what ſpirits ye are of, nor whoſe Deſigne you drive therein; they have the ſame Seal for their Ministry that</hi> Paul <hi>had for his Apostleſhip,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.2, <hi>they have by it converted not a few to Christ, and that too as the truth is in Jeſus, which we do not finde to be the property of Antichrist or his Ministers. An orderly call addes both beauty and efficacy to the Word preached. Take heed by dispa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging them or their Function in the eyes or eares of their People, you weaken not their hands in the Lords worke, for which they ought to be had in estimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or of being an occaſion of putting out ſuch lights, who have ſhaken the kingdom of Darkneſſe, and by the bleſſing of God upon their labours have made</hi> England <hi>famous for powerfull Preaching and profeſſing in all the Christian World, and thoſe of you that are ſonnes and not baſtards, I am confident under God have had them for your fathers. Beware of a ſpirit of Antichriſt amongſt your ſelves, it is he that pretends to both Swords, and whoſe comming is after the working of Satan with all power and ſignes and lying wonders, and with all deceivableneſſe of unrighteouſneſſe,</hi> viz. <hi>ſalſe Doctrine and Errour, and the reaſon is rendred, becauſe they receive not the love of the truth, which is not then ſo light a matter as you take it for, when as the Goſpel of peace (if it understand it ſelfe aright) bids us contend for it, against men of heretical judgements. Dote not ſo much upon the word</hi> gifted Brethren, <hi>it is a proud word ſince extraordinaries ceaſed, and makes grace a younger brother, thoſe of you that are gracious, communicate your graces and ſpiritual experiences unto edification as fellow-members and private Christians, and be not many Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117612:4"/>in opinion, do not the worke of an Office in the Church (I ſpeak not of caſes extraordinary, which have their extraordinary priviledges and diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) Without being an Officer of the Church, one of thoſe that Christ hath ordained. Gifts no more intitle men to publique Offices in the Church than in the Common-wealth or Army, without a call. An outward call is not nothing. Study not confuſion, God is not at all the God of it, and least of all in his Church. There is no better nor no worſe argument agaiust you than that of Chriſt,</hi> The tree is knowne by his fruits. <hi>Some of your Converts I have ſeen and talked with, full of opinion but very empty of grace and the vital Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Religion, put them upon diſpute and they are old excellent, but upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian communion and they have not a word to ſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The good old <hi>Puritan</hi> that is not aſhamed of faith and repentance is the name of ſubſtance, your <hi>Proſelites</hi> muſt needs be ſtrange crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that are ſtrangers to the ſincere milke of the Word, borne and bred a mongſt fooliſh janglings, for your Sermons which tends to ſingularity and plurality of opinions, conduce not to devotion but to diſputation, which old Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> (whoſe very name is pretious for his practicall piety) was wont to ſay, made his heart the worſe a long time after.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And indeed a practicall hearted Chriſtian loves not to hear truth doubted, for that makes faith take wind, and the whole Soul conſequently fare the worſe, but knows they are ordained to other uſe,</hi> viz <hi>to be a whet-ſton to our graces not to our wits. Such preaching diſputants batch addle egges, fil empty hearts with empty no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. How forcible are right words, but what doth your arguing availe? but to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune the ſoule. Opinion begets pride, and that keeps out every thing but it ſelfe. If you will needs preach, then preach truth and not error, as you will anſwer it at the dreadfull day of judgement, and gather the ſenſe of Scripture from its ſcope and drift, comparing ſpirituall things with ſpirituall; and not incoherent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly making it ſpeak what it never meant. You have been victorious over Errour, therefore let not error at the laſt get victory over you, like the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving conquered Idolaters, worſhpped their Idols. Cry not up liberty of Conſcience to the loſſe of Conſcience, and countenancing licentiouſneſſe of opinion, ſee ye not how his Majeſty himſelfe pretends deeply to its for the ſetting up prerogative and Epiſcopacy. What Snake may not lye hid under that herbe? when once it's grown a word in faſhion. Liberty of conſcience will bee as common, as not guilty at the Aſſizes, and of equall credit. Divine Truth is always the ſame, of an inflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nature, various not according to mens judgements, ſhall the judgement of a man be the rule of Gods un-erring Truth? Truth is truth, and error error, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men thinke it to bee ſo or no, principles of nature vary not like languages, and if they bee inviolable, and indiſpenſible, much more is Divinity, for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117612:5"/>known will of God is obliging, which way ſoever it be revealed, whether by nature, or by the word, though againſt nature, as when</hi> Abraham <hi>was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to kill his ſon; or above nature, as in the union of the two natures in one perſon, or the being of three perſons in one God-head, nay of the two; the word is the more foreible and binding, becauſe nature is ſo much defaced; therefore not the Law given to the</hi> Iſraelites <hi>the more obliging, and their ſins the more provoking. Opinion ought not to be the rule of things, but the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing is ſelfe. There is a Truth of God, and that but one, which we must maintaine to the death (elſe the Martyrs dyed in vaine, if for but oppoſing anothers lawfull liberty) not only in reſisting impiety, but in oppoſing hereſie.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.16. Stand ye in the wayes, and ſee, ask for the old paths, where is the good way and walk therein, and ye ſhall find reſt for your ſoules.</p>
            <p>And for Malignants that would fight againe to be ſlaves, though they had more wit before than to ſtand to it. For the ingenuouſeſt of them ſay, that if the King had got the better, the Kingdome had beene un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, they ſee ſo farre now into his diſpoſition, and yet they in hope to be ſprinkled with Court holy water, are content to ſell their birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, which their Progenitors nobly purchaſed with their blood, and they as ignobly ſell it with theirs. They are weary of peace already, which yet is a cheaper tenure to hold by then diſſeiſing, which would fall to our ſhare if they ſhould paramount, as themſelves ſtick not to ſay, and threaten to try us all for Traytors at the Kings Bench barre, where proud <hi>Mallet</hi> and pricket <hi>Heath</hi> ſhould give ſentence, and then there would be old worke for new Tiburne. <hi>Hambleten</hi> and <hi>Taffe</hi> denizoned with the Eſtates of <hi>Northumberland</hi> and <hi>Pembreeke,</hi> and their blew Ribbands to boot; as judging moſt fit, that they ſhould ride on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back that fought for S. <hi>George.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why ſhould wee engage againe, let them have ſlavery and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage without fighting for it. Thoſe of them whoſe Anceſtors gained their Honours by fighting for their Countrey, let them now loſe theirs for endeavouring to fight againſt it, a doom which their own forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers would paſſe upon them, were they alive, to ſee ſuch degenerate ſtems to grow out of ſuch noble ſtocks, for Nobility and Gentry ought not to diſtend by propagation without derivation, not by blood but by vertue. And thoſe of them who Citizen like bought their Armes and Honours, let them all be reverſed till they renew their Pattents at the old rate, and compound at Heraulds-Hall for their forfeited honours, by ſhamefull deſerting their Countrey, more worth them the Kings in Chriſtendome.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
